Hiram Williams Papers
Hiram Williams Papers
1917-1966
Williams, Hiram.
2 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter and educator. Collection includes incoming and outgoing correspondence, original book illustrations and a painting of his parents, reproductions of Williams' artwork, financial and legal material, lists of paintings, photographs of Williams and his family, and printed material. Correspondents include Luis Eades, Hobson Pittman, and art galleries and museums.
149710
Biographical History
Hiram Williams (1917-2003) was an American painter and art educator, known for his abstract figures and portrait work.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Hiram Williams Papers comprises biographical material, correspondence, artwork, writings and memorabilia of the American painter and educator. Focusing on the 1950s and 1960s, the collection -- which is occasionally interspersed with annotations supplied by Williams -- illuminates his artistic career and, to a lesser extent, his personal life.
Correspondence-subject files (Box 1) consists of incoming letter and outgoing carbons, as well as other material pertaining to art, from 1960 through 1966. Correspondence includes that of artists (Luis Eades, Hobson Pittman, William Stephens), patron Mildred Hawn, art galleries and museums (Atelier Chapman Kelley, Beaumont Art Museum, Carlin Galleries, Cushman Galleries, Museum of Modern Art, and others), the John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, and publisher Prentice-Hall.
Artwork (Box 2) encompasses original book illustrations for Williams' Notes for a Young Painter, an original painting of his parents, and numerous reproductions of his work, including photographs and negatives of several exhibitions, a mural and paintings.
An original handwritten manuscript of an unpublished novel and miscellaneous statements on art constitute Writings.
Memorabilia (Boxes 3 and 4) comprises family mementos, financial and legal material, lists of Williams' paintings (some with prices), photographs, printed material, and teaching-related items. Family memorabilia includes Williams' baby book, his father's diary from 1938, two newspaper clippings about his parents, and incoming correspondence from his mother. Financial and legal material consists of miscellaneous contracts, receipts and bank statements. Among the Photographs are some of Williams teaching at the University of Florida and miscellaneous pictures of the artist, his family and friends. Printed material contains articles, reviews, newspaper clippings, and exhibition catalogs and invitations.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence-subject files are arranged alphabetically by correspondence. Artwork, Writings and Memorabilia are each arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Eades, Luis.; Pittman, Hobson, 1900-; Williams, Hiram.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Illustrations.; Photographs.; Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Hiram Williams, 1967.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Atelier Chapman Kelley, 1963; 1965 (Box 1)
  - Beaumont Art Museum, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Bocour Artist Colors, Inc., 1965 (Box 1)
  - Carlin Galleries, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Cushman Gallery, Inc., 1960-1962; undated (Box 1)
  - Delray Beach Library, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Eades, Luis, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Galleries of Frank J. Oehlschlager, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation
    - Correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Hawn, Mildred, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Junior Service League of Longview, Texas, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Kelley, Chapman, See Atelier Chapman Kelley.
  - Felix Landau Gallery, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1960; undated (Box 1)
  - Nordness Gallery, 1961-1966; undated (Box 1)
  - Nye Galleries, 1961-1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania State University, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Pittman, Hobson, 1963; undated (Box 1)
  - Pratt Graphic Art Center, 1962; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1962-1965 (Box 1)
  - Stephens, William, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, A-Z (Box 1)
- Artwork
  - Original book illustrations for Notes for a Young Painter, ballpoint pen (Box 2)
  - Original painting, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs and negatives
    - Exhibitions, 1959; undated (Box 2)
    - Mural at Penn State University, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
    - Paintings, by title, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Reproductions, 1960; 1962,; 1963 (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Novel, untitled, original handwritten manuscript; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Statements on art, 1959; 1963,; 1964,; undated (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Family, 1917; 1938,; 1956-1963,; undated (Box 3)
  - Financial and legal, 1962-1965; contracts, receipts, bank statements (Box 3)
  - Lists of paintings, undated; some include prices (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 3)
  - Printed material
    - Articles and reviews, 1952-1966; undated (Box 3)
    - Clippings, 1952-1966; undated (Box 3)
    - Exhibition catalogs, group shows, 1951-1963; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Exhibition catalogs, group shows, 1964-1966; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Exhibition catalogs, one-man shows, 1959-1966 (Box 4)
  - Exhibition invitations, 1952-1966; undated (Box 4)
  - Teaching-related items
    - University of Florida, 1961-1963; 1966; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - University of Texas, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)